Okay, so anyways, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף daf *Daf* is
דף ז *Daf Zayin*. We're back on the normal דף *Daf*, not
we'll try to get ahead again, but anyway, right now we start,
we pick up on ו עמוד ב *Vav amud bet*, the two
dots, about fifteen lines from the bottom, הסך בשמן המשחה Hasach b'shemen
hamishcha, *Hasach b'shemen hamishcha*. So we're going through the list of things
that get כרת karet, *Kares* for, where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I
mean the תוספתא *Tosefta* had many of the things in the list,
but is focusing on the ones that are left that don't have
too much discussion elsewhere in ש"ס Shas *Shas*. And we discussed making
the קטורת *Ketores*, making the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha *Shemen hamishcha*, and
now we're discussing one who anoints himself with the שמן המשחה shemen
hamishcha, *Shemen hamishcha* not that he made, but that is the שמן
המשחה shemen hamishcha, *Shemen hamishcha* of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis
Hamikdash*. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan: *Tanu Rabbanan*,
we taught, הסך בשמן המשחה beshemen hamishchah לבהמה וכלים פטור *Hasach b'shemen
hamishcha l'behema u'v'keilim patur*. If you use the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha,
*Shemen hamishcha* for an animal or for vessels, you are פטור *Patur*.
Now, whether it's מעילה *Me'ilah* or not is a different discussion, but
we're not discussing מעילה *Me'ilah*, we're discussing the particular prohibition of איש
אשר יסח כמהו *Ish asher yisach kamohu*. So that's the end of
the פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk* is, ואשר יתן ממנו על זר zar. *Va'asher
yitein mimenu al zar*, on a foreigner, which is understood to mean
a human being who does not have deserve for it to be
put on him. So therefore, if you put on בהמה וכלים *Behema
u'v'keilim*, you are פטור *Patur* from that prohibition.
עובדי כוכבים *Ovdei kochavim* and למתים *L'meisim*,
פטור
*Patur*.
But if it's for non-Jews and for animals and for corpses, you
are also פטור *Patur*. Now, בשלמא *Bishlama* בהמה וכלים *Behema u'v'keilim* דכתיב
*Dechtiv*, I understand by בהמה וכלים *Behema u'v'keilim* it says על בשר
אדם adam, לא יסך *Al b'sar adam lo yisach*, going back even
earlier, right before you even get to זר zar *Zar*. על בשר
אדם adam לא יסך *Al b'sar adam lo yisach*, you shall not
anoint it on the flesh of a human. ובהמה וכלים לאו lav.
אדם adam הם *U'vehema u'v'keilim lav adam heim*, and animals and vessels
aren't humans, but the specific prohibition is about humans. מתים נמי פטור
*Meisim nami patur*, and I understand that you're פטור *Patur* if you
put it on a corpse, again, bracketing the מעילה *Me'ilah* question, דכיון
דמית ליה מת מקרי ולאו אדם adam *Dekivan demis lei meis mikrei
v'lav adam*, because once a person is dead, it's called a corpse,
no longer called a person. A person stops being a person when
he dies. אלא ela, עובדי כוכבים *Ela ovdei kochavim*, אלא ela, *Ela*,
right, מת *Meis*, אלא עובדי כוכבים אמאי פטור *Ela ovdei kochavim amai
patur*?
Why is a non-Jew exempt? אדם adam, נינהו *Adam ninhu*, they're called
אדם *Adam* in the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*. So now this gets into
a fascinating and always very disturbing discussion about whether חז"ל Chazal, *Chazal*
at sometimes דורשים פסוקים pesukim *Darshim pesukim* that say אדם *Adam* to
include non-Jews and sometimes they דורשים *Darshim* it to exclude non-Jews. So
obviously the latter is always deeply disturbing and תוספות *Tosafos* in a
couple of places in ש"ס *Shas* tries to understand how come the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is inconsistent how it interprets the word אדם *Adam*.
So here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* starts with the assertion that אדם
*Adam* includes non-Jews and then it says בשלמא *Bishlama*, is that really
so?
How do you know this that אדם *Adam* includes or is that
really true? דכתיב *Dechtiv*, ואתם צאן צאן מרעיתי אדם אתם *V'atem tzon
tzon mar'isi adam atem*, you are my flock, the flock of my
shepherding, you are אדם *Adam*, אתם קרויין אדם ואין עובדי כוכבים קרויין
אדם *Atem keruyin adam v'ein ovdei kochavim keruyin adam*, you are called
אדם *Adam* and the non-Jews are not called אדם *Adam*. So the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, okay, והכתיב *V'hachtiv*, ונפש אדם ששה עשר אלף
*V'nefesh adam shisha asar aleph*, so you can't really say that, meaning
so the first question was,
where were we?
So first the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first said that they should have
been included in אדם *Adam*, then it quotes a פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*
to exclude them, and now it's saying, but no, they actually are
included in the phrase אדם *Adam*. והכתיב *V'hachtiv*, ונפש אדם ששה עשר
אלף *V'nefesh adam shisha asar aleph*, and this is talking about the
captives that they took from מדין *Midyan* and there were sixteen thousand
and it called said them אדם *Adam*, so you see they are
called אדם *Adam*. אמר ליה Amar lei *Amar lei*, so the answer
was no, ההוא לאפוקי בהמה *Ahu l'afukei behema*, there it's also talking
about the animals that they captured, so it's a contrast to the
animals, but it's not to actually say that that's the classic use
of the term. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והכתיב ואני לא
אחוס על נינוה העיר הגדולה אשר יש בה הרבה משתים עשרה רבו
אדם אשר לא ידע בין ימינו לשמאלו ובהמה רבה *V'hachtiv v'ani lo
achus al Ninveh ha'ir hagedola asher yesh bah harbe mishteim esrei ribo
adam asher lo yada bein yemino l'smolo u'vehema raba*. ובהמה רבה *U'vehema
raba*
is the end of the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*. Where does it say
אדם *Adam* there? It says, right, here. ואני לא אחוס על נינוה
העיר הגדולה אשר יש בה הרבה משתים עשרה רבו אדם אשר לא
ידע בין ימינו לשמאלו ובהמה רבה *V'ani lo achus al Ninveh ha'ir
hagedola asher yesh bah harbe mishteim esrei ribo adam asher lo yada
bein yemino l'smolo u'vehema raba*. So
there clearly it's also talking about non-Jews. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, ההוא לאפוקי בהמה *Ahu l'afukei behema*. No, that's again in contrast
to בהמה *Behema*, but if it was just occurring by itself, maybe
it would mean only ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael*. איבעית אימא *Iba'is eima*, so
that's the first answer. That they are excluded, that they are excluded
from אדם *Adam*. What?
This is really because they're trying to fit it into the
מסורה *Mesorah* that עובדי כוכבים *Ovdei kochavim* were not. But some, yes
and no, sometimes they use it as a basis of exemption and
sometimes they use it as a basis of inclusion. So as I
said, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here which is arguing it as a
basis of exemption is a very disturbing one if you take it
as a sense of like that's not, look,
let me just take a step back and say, okay, you know,
while there are differences in הלכה *Halacha* between Jews and non-Jews, you
know, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* certainly, the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* even, even
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* who very often is the one
that emphasizes differences between Jews and non-Jews in הלכה *Halacha* is the
one that
says, you know...
Anyway, the משנה Mishnah that says, you know, חביב אדם שנברא בצלם,
Chaviv adam shenivra betzelem, right?
All human beings are dear that they were created in the image
of God. חביבים ישראל שנקראו בנים למקום. Chavivim Yisrael shenikru banim lamakom.
So at the same time emphasizing the unique relationship that בני ישראל
Bnei Yisrael have with God, he underscores, you know, the fact that
all everybody is created in צלם אלקים. tzelem Elokim. On the other
hand, sadly, there are thinkers in Jewish history that have tried to
say that that non-Jews aren't created in צלם אלקים, tzelem Elokim, that
somehow even though the פסוקים pesukim obviously talks about all human beings,
you know, they say very disturbing things like that which are again
on the one hand, you know, you understand where that comes from
after living, you know, a life of oppression at the hands of
non-Jews, but nevertheless there are those
strands, but certainly overwhelmingly even without all of, you know, the even
with acknowledging the distinctions in law that exist, the idea that all
people are humans and everybody's created in צלם אלקים tzelem Elokim and
whatever, you know, is clearly the position, you know, of חז"ל, so
and of the פסוקים pesukim let alone. So the idea that it's
not called אדם, you hope that that's not making a deeper philosophical
statement. You hope that somehow, you know, or you hope that somehow
that's some technical point in terms of a דרש. drash. And sometimes
actually the גמרא Gemara emphasizes the fact that אדם is specifically said
in order to include non-Jews. So it is disturbing when the גמרא's
Gemara. actually use אדם to exclude non-Jews and there are a couple
of places in ש"ס that do it, but I do not but
to answer your question honestly, I do not believe the גמרא's Gemara
only doing it here in order to solve its problem. There are
גמרות Gemaras that actually specifically, you know, make the דרשה drasha for
example, the question about non-Jews not being מטמא באוהל metameh b'ohel for
כהנים Kohanim because it says אדם כי ימות באוהל. adam ki yamut
b'ohel. Okay, so there it is a whenever you encounter this, it
is a deeply challenging discussion in the גמרא. Gemara So for use
of that.
Yes, it's very the whole the whole statement is specious in the
sense because the way the גמרא Gemara. supports it is you know
from these פסוקים pesukim that that say well we're excluding I have
to find the exact פסוק, pasuk. but you know it's not really
it's it's using פסוקים pesukim in a way that it often does
which is just to make things come out right.
Well that's what Michael said, that it was using the פסוקים psukim,
in order to challenge the idea that אדם excluded non-Jews and then
it found a way to resolve it. So it is true here
it serves the גמרא's Gemara ends because it's trying to explain why
they're exempt by non-Jews and it serves its ends to make that
דרשה. drasha. But again, I'm saying that it would be it would
be a little, you know, dishonest to say that this is the
גמרא's Gemara only saying this for the sake of solving its immediate
problem. Okay, this is a bigger challenge and it's the use of
how the גמרא Gemara interprets אדם, sometimes specifically to include non-Jews and
sometimes specifically to exclude. Anyway, that's the first answer of the גמרא.
Gemara תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we taught in as well. הסך בשמן
המשחה,
I'm sorry did I skip a line? ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, if
you want, תני תנא קמיה דרבי אלעזר, tani tanna kamei d'Rabbi Elazar,
כל שישנו בסיכה ישנו בבל יסך. kol sheyeshno b'sicha yeshno b'val yisach.
An easier basis to exclude the non-Jew. Anybody that is prohibited for
from the prohibition of using the שמן המשחה shemen hamishchah, in this
way is prohibited from putting it on that person. So non-Jew so
Jews are prohibited to use the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishchah, right? They
have the תרי"ג מצוות, taryag mitzvot, it's not one of the שבע
מצוות בני נח. sheva mitzvot bnei Noach. So therefore it's prohibited to
go on the flesh of a Jew. וכל שאינו בסיכה אינו בבל
יסך, v'chol she'eino b'sicha eino b'val yisach, anybody that is not prohibited
is not prohibited to go on their flesh. Okay, so that's a
better an easier way of excluding non-Jews. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we've
done another ברייתא. baraita. הסך בשמן המשחה לבהמה וכלים לעובדי כוכבים ומתים
פטור. Hasach b'shemen hamishcha l'behema v'kelim l'ovdei kochavim u'metim patur. So the
same thing we said now, animals, vessels, corpses, non-Jews you're exempt. למלכים
ולכהנים, L'melachim u'l'kohanim,
if it's for kings or for priests who you remember from a
דף or two ago you actually use the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishchah.
but now you've actually used it in order to anoint them for
the first time and now they went ahead and they used it
again or you used it again on them after you've already done.
You used it a second time? Yeah. So is that a problem?
כשהיא לכהנים גדולים, K'sheh'hi l'kohanim gedolim, רבי מאיר מחייב רבי יהודה פוטר.
Rabbi Meir mechayev Rabbi Yehuda poter. Rabbi Meir obligates, says no, once
you're done with them they've done the requisite שמן המשחה, shemen hamishchah,
now you're
exempt,
now you're חייב chayav and Rabbi Yehuda exempts. Well, if they were
if they participated. וכמה יסוך ויהא חייב, V'kama yasuch v'yehei chayav,
now how much placing of oil are you do you transgress? רבי
מאיר אומר כל שהוא, Rabbi Meir omer kol shehu, רבי יהודה אומר
כזית. Rabbi Yehuda omer k'zayit. Even the smallest amount, Rabbi Yehuda says
no it has to be כזית. k'zayit. So now the גמרא Gemara
says והאמר רבי יהודה פטור, v'ha'amar Rabbi Yehuda patur, wait a minute
Rabbi Yehuda just got through saying that if you do it on
a king or כהן גדול Kohen Gadol you're exempt. So how could
now he say a כזית? k'zayit? No, no, no. כי פטר רבי
יהודה גבי מלכים וכהנים. Ki patar Rabbi Yehuda gabei melachim v'kohanim. Okay,
that was when he was talking there was two debates, one was
priests and כהנים, Kohanim, excuse me, one was kings and כהנים, Kohanim,
that case he says you're exempt, but גבי הדיוט מחייב, gabei hedyot
mechayev, a normal person of course he agrees you're חייב, chayav, that's
the פסוק. pasuk So when we said how much, we don't know
how we don't mean how much by kings and by כהנים. Kohanim.
When we said... debate is kings and כהנים *Kohanim*. Then we have
another question. When anyone when you do it on a person you're
not allowed to do it on, how much do you need to
transgress and there there's a debate of a כל שהוא kol shehu.
*kol shehu* and a כזית kezayit *kezayit*. So two separate debates. Let's
see what the debate is about. רב מאיר ורב יהודה במאי פליגי
*Rav Meir ve-Rav Yehuda be-mai peligi*? What are they debate about? In
now we're first talking about the second debate about the quantity you
need to transgress. אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef בהאי פליגי *Amar
Rav Yosef be-hai peligi*. They debate the following thing. רב מאיר סבר
על בשר אדם לא ייסך al besar adam lo yisach. כתיב *Rav
Meir savar al besar adam lo yisach ketiv*. You should not put
it on the flesh of humans. וכתיב ואשר יתן ממנו על זר
zar, *u-chetiv va-asher yiten mimenu al zar*. So the prohibition mentions ייסך
*yisach* to anoint, והכרת *ve-ha-karet* says that if you place יתן *yiten*.
So they're different verbs. So now we're going to make the following
דרשה drashah. *drasha*. They imply different quantities. מה סיכה sichah כל שהוא
*ma sicha kol shehu*, anoint is even the smallest amount. We never
have a concept that the תורה Torah, *Torah* says don't anoint elsewhere
that we define it in terms of a minimum quantity. So given
that there's no other basis for saying a minimum quantity, we'll say
סיכה sichah *sicha* means even the smallest amount. אף af. נתינה netinah,
כל שהוא *af netina kol shehu*. When it says place, although there
are other times we דרשן *darshan* to place in ways of more
of a minimum amount, because it's linked to סיכה *sicha*, we say
here too it's a minimum. So starting from סיכה *sicha*, which is
always which is never interpreted as a minimum, we say נתינה netinah
*netina* also means a minimum. So we have סיכה *sicha*
and נתינה netinah. *netina* based on a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of סיכה
*sicha*. רב יהודה סבר *Rav Yehuda savar*, and here's this debate is
תרתי שמעתתא בדברי רב *tartei shemateta be-divrei Rav*. רב יהודה סבר ילפינן
נתינה netinah דעל זר zar. מנתינה דעלמא *Rav Yehuda savar yalfinan netina
de-al zar mi-netina de-alma*. No, we use נתינה netinah *netina*, we interpret
it in the classic way. מה נתינה דעלמא כזית kezayit. *ma netina
de-alma kezayit*, the same way it normally means a כזית kezayit, *kezayit*.
Where do you know that from? You learn it from the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* that speaks about somebody who eats תרומה trumah *terumah* and
from
that belongs to a כהן Kohen *kohen*, and it says that he
has to give it back to a כהן Kohen. *kohen*. And we
say that eating, since it starts by an act of eating, therefore
we're talking about a כזית *kezayit*. So the giving, the נתינה *netina*
there also refers to a כזית *kezayit*. So the same way we
make that דרשה drashah *drasha* elsewhere by תרומה trumah. *terumah*, so here
too we make the דרשה drashah *drasha* that נתינה *netina* is מה
נתינה דעלמא אף נתינה דעל זר כזית *ma netina de-alma af netina
de-al zar kezayit*. Here too it's by a כזית *kezayit*. Which raises
the interesting question, which is, would he just say that you need
a כזית *kezayit* in order to get כרת karet *karet* because of
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says נתינה *netina* by כרת karet *karet*, or
would he say you even need a get a you need a
כזית *kezayit* to get the to transgress the לאו lav, *lav*? It
sounds like that even to transgress the לאו *lav*, even מחייב *mechayiv*
normally means מחייב *mechayiv* for the transgression, not necessarily for the כרת
karet *karet*. So presumably once נתינה *netina* means a כזית *kezayit*, it
goes back and applies it to סיכה *sicha*. But again, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s not clear about that. So that's one debate. Do you
emphasize the word נתינה *netina*, emphasize the word סיכה *sicha*? Is it
a כל שהוא *kol shehu*, is it a כזית *kezayit*? That's question
number one. Let's get to the next question, which is kings and
כהנים *Kohanim*. אבל סיכה דמשח מלכים וכהנים דברי הכל כל שהוא *aval
sicha de-mishach melachim ve-kohanim divrei ha-kol kol shehu*. Now
when it comes to the issue about kings and כהנים *Kohanim*, that
is כל שהוא *kol shehu*. Now what does it mean it's כל
שהוא *kol shehu*? Meaning, meaning didn't
רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* say that you don't transgress when you do
kings and מלכים *melachim*? So it means that when you do it,
presumably it means that when you're doing the מצוה *mitzvah*, not when
you're transgressing, when you're doing the מצוה *mitzvah* of כהנים *Kohanim* and
of kings, so there actually it is even a כל שהוא *kol
shehu*. Okay, now exactly doesn't exactly say where you know that from.
Just one second. We had it before, it was
like two drops of oil on his head.
Right, right. But but how do you know? Maybe I mean it's
also right.
Okay, fine.
So again, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s not clear exactly where you learn
that from. Now let's look at that debate, the debate about kings
and כהנים *Kohanim*. ואמר רב יוסף במאי פליגי רב מאיר ורב יהודה
גבי מלכים וכהנים *ve-amar Rav Yosef be-mai peligi Rav Meir ve-Rav Yehuda
gabei melachim ve-kohanim*? What's that debate about? רב מאיר סבר אשר יתן
ממנו על זר כתיב ומלך וכהן השתא זר נינהו *Rav Meir savar
asher yiten mimenu al zar ketiv u-melech ve-kohen hashta zar ninhu*. It
says if you put it on a foreigner, and now once they've
been anointed and there's no longer a מצוה *mitzvah* to anoint them,
so now they're considered foreign. There's no purpose, they have no right
to be anointed a second time, and therefore you'll transgress even with
them. רב יהודה סבר בעינן עד דאיכא זרות מתחלתו ועד סופו *Rav
Yehuda savar be'inan ad de-ika zarut mi-techilato ve-ad sofo*. Actually that would
seem maybe even, you know, to to make a little more sense.
A foreigner suggests the idea that you have complete it's completely foreign
to you. So that's what he says. Only if you were a
foreigner from the beginning to the end. Although now you have no
rights to be anointed again, originally you did have a right to
be anointed, so vis-a-vis the שמן המשחה shemen hamishchah, *shemen ha-mishcha*, you're
not considered a foreigner. Now actually it's interesting because first of all
it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't say כהנים גדולים *Kohanim
Gedolim*, which is presume now the question is that I keep on
saying כהן Kohen גדול *Kohen Gadol* because a כהן Kohen. גדול *Kohen
Gadol* was what do you call it? Was anointed on a regular
basis. On the other hand, you could have asked that even kings
weren't anointed on a regular basis because as we learned in the
previous גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, if it's a מלך בן מלך *melech ben
melech* and there's no מחלוקת *machloket* about it, you wouldn't anoint them.
So you could have a king that wasn't anointed. Now that's on
the one hand. On the other hand, you could say the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* isn't limiting itself to כהנים גדולים *Kohanim Gedolim*. I keep
on sticking in that word, but all the כהנים *Kohanim* were anointed
once, right? When they initially anointed אהרן *Aharon* and his children and
when they when they dedicated the המשכן *ha-Mishkan*. So it's possible that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not limiting itself to כהנים גדולים *Kohanim
Gedolim*, and this also answers what the question about kings. And it's
really saying since as a class כהנים *Kohanim* were once anointed, they're
not זרים zarim. *zarim*. Since as a class מלכים *melachim* could be
anointed, then they're not זר *zar*, even if this king was never
anointed. anointed, even if this כהן Kohen. was never anointed.
Include מלכי ישראל? Malchei Yisrael?
Probably not מלכי ישראל Malchei Yisrael because they're a class they never
were anointed. Okay, so it's an interesting question here when רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda exempts, is he exempting this particular one because he was
anointed in the past or even if as he was member of
a class? Because you could say you're not a זר. A זר
means a member of a class to whom this is foreign. Okay,
let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara מלך וכהן מעיקרא לאו זרים נינהו. Melech veKohen me'ikara lav
zarim ninhu. A king and a כהן Kohen originally were not זרים.
Again, as a class or individuals, it's not clear. אמר רב איקא
בריה דרב אמי Amar Rav Ika brei deRav Ami ואזלו לטעמייהו. va'azlu
letamayhu. They go according to their reasoning, whether we look at the
now or whether we look big picture. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, Baraita, בת כהן שנישאת לישראל ואכלה בתרומה. bat Kohen sheniset
leYisrael ve'achla bitrumah. Let's say you have a daughter of a כהן.
Now, a daughter of a כהן until she gets married has the
right to eat תרומה trumah. from her father's house. She marries a
ישראל, she's no longer allowed to eat תרומה. trumah, Now, she goes
out and she does eat תרומה. trumah, משלמת את הקרן ואינה משלמת
את החומש. Meshalemet et hakeren ve'eina meshalemet et hachomesh. She has to
pay back the קרן, keren, the principal of what she ate, but
she does not pay back the חומש, chomesh, the fifth, because that
is somebody that if a זר, וזר כי יאכל תרומה בשגגה. ve'zar
ki yochal trumah bishgagah. Okay, if a foreigner eats תרומה, trumah, they
pay back the basis and a fifth. So on the one hand,
right now she's not allowed to eat תרומה, trumah okay, it's still
a biblical prohibition for her to eat תרומה, trumah but in terms
of this פסוק pasuk of paying back a fifth, that's about a
זר. And she's not a foreigner because she originally was able to.
Not only she originally was able to, we'll see in a minute
she might go back to eating תרומה terumah if her husband dies.
Okay, now is she a חללה chalalah too? Because she marries a...
Well, that's a good question. So that's part maybe the question about
whether this is because of her past or her future, her potential
future. ומיתתה בשריפה. Umitatah bisreifah. If she commits adultery, she's treated like
a בת כהן bat Kohen who commits adultery, even though now she
is no longer has the status of a בת כהן, bat Kohen,
right, when... and therefore she gets שריפה, sreifah, not חנק. chenek. Now,
נישאת לאחד מן הפסולים. niset le'echad min hapsulim. Now, let's say however
she married somebody that is פסול, pasul, that actually
Michael's question, that would invalidate her. משלמת קרן וחומש ומיתתה בחנק דברי
רבי מאיר. Meshalemet keren vechomesh umitatah bichenek divrei Rabbi Meir. In that
case, she totally will never go back to be a בת כהן
bat Kohen because she's become a חללה, chalalah, and therefore she would
have the full... she would pay the fifth and she would get
חנק chenek if she committed adultery. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim what? Or
she just got from marrying
a כהן.
If she marries a חלל, chalal, then even if her husband dies,
she can't marry a... חלל, chalal, then she becomes a חללה, chalalah,
and even if her husband dies, she can't go back and marry
a כהן. Okay, I think that was exactly what you were asking,
right Michael? Okay, fine. So, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim אחת זו ואחת זו achat zo ve'achat zo
משלמת את הקרן ואינה משלמת את החומש. meshalemet et hakeren ve'eina meshalemet
et hachomesh. No, even if she cannot go back, even if she
is done from being ever getting a בת כהן bat Kohen status,
since she was that in the past, forgetting the future, she will
always pay the principal and not the fifth, ומיתתה בשריפה umitatah bisreifah
and get שריפה. sreifah. She always retains that status. So you see
here, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says she's only going to have a
בת כהן bat Kohen status because she might have it in the
future. And therefore she even has it now. Once it's cut off
as a future possibility, she no longer has... she's then considered completely
a זרה, zarah, a foreigner. Whereas the חכמים Chachamim say, which would
be רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, she can never be called a זרה.
zarah. Even if she'll never get back to that status, she was
once in that פרשה, parshah, and therefore she can never be a
foreigner.
Unless she was born... like the child...
Right, that would probably be different, even according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. But again, notice there, that's that particular person was once in
that category. Again, it goes back to our question whether רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir were talking only if that
particular person was once anointed בשמן המשחה or just as a member
of the class. Okay, that's in terms of the interesting debate about
כהן and kings. אמר רב יוסף מחלוקת בנתינת שמן המשחה ובשינוי דשנינה.
machloket binetinat shemen hamishchah uveshinuy deshanina. The debate is about the placing
of the... meaning now going back to the question about whether it's
a כזית or כל שהוא. It's specifically about שמן המשחה, shemen hamishchah
whether you emphasize the word סיכה or you emphasize the word נתינה,
based on the way we explained it. אבל נתינה דעלמא, Aval netinah
de'alma, normally what does the word נתינה mean? Meaning the way we
framed it, that it was about specifically שמן המשחה, shemen hamishchah whether
you emphasize סיכה or נתינה. אבל נתינה דעלמא, Aval netinah de'alma, normally
what the word נתינה means, דברי הכל כזית. divrei hakol kezayit. Everybody
would agree that normally means a כזית. This is a very local
debate. Normally נתינה means a כזית, like in the case of תרומה
that we mentioned before. So that's just underscoring that he, you know,
the previous way in which the debate was framed and limited. גופא.
Gufa. Now let's go back to what we said before. תני תנא
קמיה דרבי אליעזר Tani tana kamei deRabbi Eliezer חושך השמן בסך השמן
ועל ייסך choshech hashemen basach hashemen ve'al yisach וכל שאינו בסך אינו
בעל ייסך. vekol she'eino basach eino be'al yisach. Only if you are
prohibited to do it, shall it not go on your flesh. If
you're not prohibited to do it, like a non-Jew, then there's no
prohibition of putting it on a non-Jew's flesh. Again, we're bracketing the
נעילה Ne'ilah questions, this is only about the question of the specific
prohibition of שמן shemen, המשחה. אמר ליה amar lei, שפיר קאמרת. shapir
kamarta. That's a good דרשה. And
this is what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said back to the תנא.
tana. The תנא tana was just teaching something that he had memorized,
and here רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying back to him, ah,
that's a good point. Why? לא ייסך כתיב. lo yisach ketiv. It
says לא ייסך. lo yisach. על בשר אדם לא ייסך. That's in
the passive, it shall not be put on the flesh of a
human, but it's a double
יוד. yud. So
Yeah, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* can do what it wants. So anyway, and therefore
which is called the causative. So the same word which is the
passive could be if you rearrange the letters to be the causative,
and therefore the same person who can you not whose flesh can
you not put it on לא ייסך *lo yisach* the person who
is prohibited לא יסיך *lo yasich* the same type of person who
can't put it on somebody's flesh. So it also therefore it only
applies to Jews. Okay. תני רבי Rabbi חנינא קמיה דרבא *Tani Rebbe
Chanina kamei d'Rava*. So Rebbe Chanina taught in front of Rava, מניין
לכהן גדול שנטל משמן המשחה שעל ראשו ונתנו על בני מעיו מניין
שהוא חייב *minayin l'kohen gadol she'natal mishemen hamishcha she'al rosho v'nasno al
bnei me'av, minayin shehu chayav*? Assuming here we are saying that a
כהן גדול *kohen gadol* is pro- does transgress. Now we're saying explicitly
כהן גדול *kohen gadol*. So assuming we're taking the approach of רבי
Rabbi מאיר *Rebbe Meir* that a כהן גדול *kohen gadol* will transgress
once he's been anointed using the שמן המשחה *shemen hamishcha*. So he
is now sort of saying or I mean or whatever he's repeating
the position essentially of רבי Rabbi מאיר *Rebbe Meir*. How do you
know this is true? That even if he takes meaning but he's
going one step further. It's not like okay, that was last week.
Now רבי Rabbi. מאיר *Rebbe Meir* says you can't put it on
the כהן גדול *kohen gadol* because he was already anointed. No, no,
no. How about if right after he was anointed using the same
oil that he was anointed with, he now that the anointing is
done takes some of that oil and like rubs it on his
stomach. Okay. So it's the exact same oil. How do you know
that he's transgressed within the approach of רבי Rabbi מאיר *Rebbe Meir*
that כהנים *kohanim* transgress? So he says מניין שהוא חייב *minayin shehu
chayav*, how do you know he transgresses? שנאמר על בשר אדם לא
ייסך *shenemar al b'sar adam lo yisach*, shall not be placed on
the flesh of a human. Not exactly clear where he gets it
from that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Okay. So anyway let's see what the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says.
This is just another part of his בשר *basar* I guess?
I know or any אדם *adam*, any person. I don't know. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now goes on אמר ליה רב אחא
בריה דרבא לרב אשי מאי שנא מהא דתניא Detanya, *Amar lei Rav
Acha brei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi, mai shna mei ha d'tanya*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not really challenge the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. It
just wants to know one minute, how does that fit with the
general principle we have? What's the general principle? It says מאי שנא
*mai shna* or maybe the דרשה *drasha* was, maybe I should say
the following the דרשה *drasha* was the following. Since he is prohibited
maybe it's the flip of what we said before. Since he's prohibited
to place the שמן המשחה *shemen hamishcha* on somebody else, he's also
prohibited to have it on himself. Meaning before we used it to
exclude non-Jews, maybe now we're using to include כהנים *kohanim*. Somebody who
is prohibited, that person is always going to be prohibited also as
the object of the anointing. So maybe that's the דרשה *drasha* the
flip of what we said before.
Would a priest be prohibited because wouldn't he become a king? Or
you know is he like not in the class of king because
I don't know.
You ask רבי Rabbi. מאיר *Rebbe Meir*? No, that's the question I
asked before whether it's the individual or the class. So anyway here
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like רבי Rabbi. מאיר *Rebbe Meir* that
but even if it's the very same oil itself. So אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי מאי שנא מהא דתניא *amar lei
Rav Acha brei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi, mai shna mei ha d'tanya*, how
is it different from what we taught in a ברייתא baraita. *braisa*?
כהן שסך בשמן של תרומה *Kohen she'sach b'shemen shel truma*, let's say
a כהן *kohen* put תרומה *truma* oil on his body, you know
he rubbed himself with it. בן בתו ישראל *Ben bito Yisrael*, even
his Jewish grandson, now it's not limited to this but it's just
giving a common example, right you can have a Jewish grandson, a
ישראל *Yisrael* I should say, meaning not Jewish but non-כהן *kohen*, his
daughter married
a ישראל *Yisrael*. So that so his grandson but it really means
any ישראל *Yisrael*, מתעגל בו ואינו חושש *mitagel bo v'eino choshesh*, can
sort of like you know cuddle with it and you know and
you don't have to be afraid that the תרומה *truma* oil is
now getting on somebody else. So you know again it could just
be a simpler thing. Let's say a כהן *kohen* used תרומה *truma*
oil on his hands, he can shake somebody's hand. You don't have
to be concerned once a כהן *kohen* used תרומה *truma* oil that
now somebody else will touch it and benefit from it. Why? Why
is it misuse of תרומה *truma*? How is it different than this
case of the שמן המשחה *shemen hamishcha*? So he says אמר ליה
*amar lei*, no it's a different פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. התם ומתו בו
כי יחללוהו כתיב *Hasam umesu bo ki yechalelu ksiv*, they will die
a non-כהן *kohen* who benefits from a תרומה *truma* because they have
desecrated it. כיון דחלליה אתחל *Keivan d'challei itchal*, once it was already
not desecrated but once it was made חולין *chullin*, once it was
used it no longer had its קדושה kedushah, *kedusha* status. So since
the כהן *kohen* used the תרומה *truma*, he used it for a
you know a normal type of a purpose, it took it out
of its sort of קדושה *kedusha* status, it desacralized it. So the
use of it makes it considered to have now gone out of
its קדושה *kedusha* status. It was used for a you know it
was used for a human being and that somehow desacralizes it. So
that's no longer considered to be in its קדושה *kedusha* status. So
why don't we say the same by שמן המשחה *shemen hamishcha*? אבל
גבי שמן המשחה כתיב *Aval gabei shemen hamishcha ksiv* because there's a
פסוק *pasuk*, כי נזר שמן משחת אלהיו עליו *ki nezer shemen mishchas
elokav alav*, this is by the כהן גדול *kohen gadol*, because the
crown of the anointing of his God is on him. So even
after it's on him it calls it נזר משחת אלהיו *nezer mishchas
elokav*. It calls it the anointing of his God. שמן משחה קרי
רחמנא *Shemen mishcha karei rachmana*, it calls it the anointing oil even
after it's been placed on him. אף על גב דאיתא עליו לא
אתחל *Af al gav d'isa alav lo itchal*, it retains its status.
So therefore it remains a prohibition. Now of course you could say
that if you wanted to conceptually explain the difference, right you could
say that one is a misuse of the קדושה *kedusha*, right and
therefore the קדושה *kedusha* is being so by the תרומה *truma*, so
once somehow the קדושה *kedusha* has been put to use you can't
misuse it, it's already... ...and put to use, whereas by the שמן
המשחה it's not the misuse of the קדושה, it's a specific prohibition
of שמן המשחה, right, by the תרומה it's not unique to the
שמן, here's specifically about the שמן המשחה, so it's always identified by
as the שמן המשחה even after it's been used. Okay, so that
is שמן המשחה discussion. Now we are done with the גמרא's Gemara,
individual analysis, it was a long list, could have gone on and
on, but it took particular things to focus on. Now we get
to the summary statement at the end of the משנה. Mishnah, So
the first one is on this entire list of כריתות, keritot, you
get a חטאת chatat if you did it בשוגג beshogeg and you
bring an אשם תלוי asham talui if you're not sure whether you
did it or not. I'll read you the line, it says על
אלו חייבין על זדונו כרת, al elu chayavin al zedono karet, if
you do it willfully, excuse me, you get כרת, kares ועל שגגתו
חטאת, ve'al shigagato chatat, if you did it unintentionally you get חטאת,
chatat, ועל לא הודע שלהם אשם תלוי, ve'al lo hoda shelahem asham
talui, but if you're not certain that you did it you bring
an אשם תלוי. asham talui. And then it says חוץ, chutz, with
the exception of ממיטמי מקדש וקדשיו, mimitamei mikdash vekodashav, if somebody is
טמא tamei and goes into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, we just
read that on שבת, Shabbat, מפני שהוא בעולה ויורד, mipnei shehu be'oleh
veyored,
there you bring a קרבן korban that varies in terms of value.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to try to explain what exactly that
means. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara קתני חוץ ממיטמי
מקדש וקדשיו, katani chutz mimitamei mikdash vekodashav,
so it's except from טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tum'at mikdash vekodashav. ממי מפיק
ליה? mimai mapik lei? What did it exclude it from? When you're
טמא tamei and going into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash you get
כרת kares if you did it willfully, you bring a חטאת chatat
if you did it unintentionally, maybe not a standard חטאת, chatat, but
you do bring a חטאת. chatat. So what does it mean except
from טמא מקדש וקדשיו? tamei mikdash vekodashav? So the גמרא Gemara says,
right, הכי קתני, hachi katani, it means חוץ ממיטמי מקדש וקדשיו שאין
מביא אשם תלוי. chutz mimitamei mikdash vekodashav she'ein mevi asham talui. Does
it mean that the person who is טמא tamei that eats a
קרבן korban and goes into the בית המקדש doesn't do any of
those things of the list? No, the first two you are in
the category, you are in the first two categories. You do have
כרת kares and you do bring a חטאת chatat if you do
it בשוגג. beshogeg. You're not in the third thing of the list.
The third thing in the list is אשם תלוי asham talui and
therefore an אשם תלוי, asham talui, which is if you did it,
if you're doubtful, you bring an אשם, asham, is only if that
if you definitely did it unintentionally, you bring a fixed חטאת, chatat,
חטאת קבוע. chatat kavua. Something that you bring a חטאת עולה ויורד,
chatat oleh veyored, a variable cost חטאת, chatat, there if you're not
certain, you do not bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says fine. So now that we're done with
that, that's טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tum'at mikdash vekodashav, you only bring אשם
תלוי asham talui for fixed value חטאות. chataot. Now the גמרא Gemara
wants to talk about other things we might have excluded from the
list. וניתני נמי חוץ משעבר עליו יום הכיפורים שאין מביא אשם תלוי.
unitni nami chutz mishe'avar alav Yom HaKippurim she'ein mevi asham talui. How
about somebody who went through יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? After you go
through יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, we assume יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones
for all of your not known sins. Now it doesn't atone for
a חטאת chatat if you're still obligated in a חטאת, chatat, you
bring it after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but it does atone for
an אשם תלוי asham talui since you were not, it's not about
a definite sin anyway. So once יום כיפור Yom Kippur has passed,
we learn in another place, not here, we're not going to do
the דרשה here, that you don't bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui.
So why did the משנה mishna. say, once all we're doing is
excluding from אשם תלוי, asham talui, even if you're in the risk,
even if you do get כרת kares and a חטאת, chatat, so
also exclude the case of somebody who went through יום כיפור? Yom
Kippur?
You could
say you wait until יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? You could, if you're
willing to be vulnerable until that time to whatever punishment is appropriate.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, let's see, שאין מביא אשם תלוי,
she'ein mevi asham talui, so אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, כי
קתני היכא דאיתיה לחטאת רחמנא פטריה. ki katani heicha de'iteih lechatat Rachmana
patrei. We're talking about a guy that normally, you know, is in
the category of a normal חטאת chatat and you are fundamentally although
excluded from an אשם תלוי. asham talui. אבל יום הכיפורים ליתיה לחטאת
דכפר ליה. aval Yom HaKippurim leiteih lechatat dekaper lei.
In case of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, now it's not really ליתיה
לחטאת leiteih lechatat because you still bring a חטאת, chatat, so the
שיטה מקובצת Shitah Mekubetzet switches the גרסא girsa to ליתיה לחטאה דכפר
ליה. leiteih lechata'ei dekaper lei. His
sin is no longer an issue, it was atoned for. So we're
talking about a guy that has the sin but somehow the possible
sin but doesn't have to bring a קרבן korban for it. By
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, we're talking about that the sin was wiped
clean. So we're not talking about other ways you get out of
an אשם. asham. Yes, there are other ways you get out of
an אשם תלוי, asham talui, you could get it wiped clean. We're
talking about ways in which you fundamentally normally should bring an אשם
asham and somehow this particular sin is excluded. And that is a
case of מקדש וקדשיו, mikdash vekodashav, that your sin is there but
somehow you're still excluded. Okay, רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, so
that's one answer. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says במבעט, bimva'et,
somebody who basically kicks, rebels. דקאמר אין יום הכיפורים מכפר, dekamar ein
Yom HaKippurim mechaper, I don't want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to atone
for me. Okay, so that type of a person that said I
don't want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to atone for my sin, you
know what God, I'll handle it from here, I got it, I'll
take the חטאת, chatat, I don't want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to
work for me. That type of a person would have to bring
his אשם תלוי asham talui even after יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Does
he say that before יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? I presumably,
before it works. So presumably sometime before יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. דאי
הדר ביה בתר יום הכיפורים בעי לאתויי אשם תלוי. de'ei hadar beih
batar Yom HaKippurim ba'ei le'atuyei asham talui. There if he did תשובה,
teshuvah, he does have to bring it after, I mean after יום
כיפור Yom Kippur he said, you know what, I think I actually
could use to be atoned for this sin. So in that case
he would have to still bring his אשם תלוי. asham talui. So
basically we didn't exclude יום כיפור Yom Kippur because it's not... always
going to get you off the hook, you could say I don't
want it to work for me. Obviously the first answer is a
much easier answer where it's just talking about whether it's the type
of sin that requires an אשם asham or not the type as
opposed to other ways that you can solve the problem. Okay, so
why anyway that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. So why didn't
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish give that answer although that seems to be
a more far-fetched answer? ריש לקיש סבר, Reish Lakish savar, so now
the גמרא Gemara is getting to get into a fascinating question about
what does יום כיפור Yom Kippur atone for or not. So here
rather than saying that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish just gave a better
answer based on just not you know a simple read of the
of the משנה, it's going to say it's a fundamental debate whether
this actually atones or not. סבר מבעיט נמי מכפר ליה יום הכיפורים.
Savar mivait nami mechaper lei Yom HaKippurim. You know what? Even a
guy that says I don't want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to atone
for me, it'll still atone for you, which is pretty radical. And
now we're going to get into some radical ideas about how powerful
יום כיפור Yom Kippur could be. ובפלוגתא, U-bi-plugta, and this is part
of another of of another debate. I mean it parallels a debate
of different אמוראים. Amoraim. האומר לא יתכפר לי חטאתי. Ha-omer lo yiskaper
li chatati. Let's say somebody says by a חטאת, chatat, you know
what? I'm going to bring the חטאת chatat because I have to
bring it, but I don't want it to atone for me. You
know, either I want to I'm just happy keeping my sin or
I'll do תשובה, teshuvah, I don't want my חטאת chatat to work
for me. I'll bring it but I don't want it to atone
for me. Will it atone anyway? Yes. אביי אמר אינו מכפר. Abaye
amar eino mechaper. It doesn't atone, you don't want it to atone.
רבא אמר מכפר. Rava amar mechaper. Whether you want it or not,
you brought it, it's going to effect, it'll atone. So, היכי דמי
לא תקרב? heichi dami lo tikarev? If you say I don't want
to bring my חטאת, chatat, I'm only bringing it because you're forcing
me, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דלא מכפר. de-kulei alma lo peligi de-lo
mechaper. Everybody agrees it doesn't work. דכתיב יקריב אותו, De-ketiv yakriv oto,
right? We have this in ערכין, Arachin, you should bring it, this
is
לרצונו, lirtzono, from which we learn the דרשה that it means that
you have to bring it out of your own will and desire.
You if you bring something עד שיאמר רוצה אני, ad she-yomar rotzeh
ani, but if you don't say רוצה אני, rotzeh ani, then it's
not going to work. So it can't be that you're saying I
don't want to. כי פליגי דאמר תקרב ולא תתכפר. Ki peligi de-amar
tikarev ve-lo titchaper. He says fine, bring it, but I don't want
it to be atone. אביי אמר אין מכפר, Abaye amar ein mechaper,
it doesn't atone, דאמר לא תתכפר, de-amar lo titchaper, says he doesn't
want it to work. רבא אמר מכפר, Rava amar mechaper, it does
atone. כיון דאמר תקרב, Keivan de-amar tikarev, since he agreed to have
it
brought, כפרה ממילא אתי, kaparah mi-meila ati, the כפרה kaparah will happen
whether you want it or not. Now part of this debate might
be, one way of understanding this, although not necessarily about יום כיפור
Yom Kippur but about a חטאת, chatat, if we've had this discussion
before that a חטאת, chatat, let me sort of give you the
opposite extreme. The גמרא Gemara said a few days ago that if
you have a case of a תינוק שנשבה, tinok she-nishba, somebody who
grew up thinking he was not Jewish, right, and he sins that
he and he violates שבת Shabbos a thousand times or whatever, he
brings a קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, at least one of these. So
the question is why does he have to bring? He thought he
was not Jewish, there's no fault, there's no guilt. So part of
the answer is because a חטאת chatat is not just about guilt
and fault. It's about the fact that metaphysically there was a sin
done and that sin has to somehow be rectified or cleansed in
some metaphysical way and that's the bringing of a חטאת. chatat. So
it's not just about your guilt. Actually some say that's the difference
between אשם asham and חטאת. chatat. אשם הוא אשום אשם להשם. Asham
hu ashom asham la-Hashem. He has been he has been you know
guilty to God. It focuses on the person. אשום, Ashom, you have
been guilty. So an אשם asham sometimes in English translated as a
guilt offering whereas a חטאת chatat is a sin offering, it's atoning
for the sin. So therefore you could say if that's true then
even without fault it can it fix it's needed to fix the
sin. This is maybe the parallel. Even if somebody's not interested in
his personal atonement, it's not about you. Everything's about
you. The world doesn't revolve around you. It's about the sin. So
you bring the חטאת, chatat, the sin somehow gets wiped off even
if you don't want it. Now that's your sin though. I understand.
But okay, but once it's it's cleaned up. Okay now that's about
however that doesn't exactly work for יום. Yom. Now I'm not sure
maybe it does, maybe we're saying the same thing by יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. But anyway by יום כיפור Yom Kippur we definitely think
it focuses much more on the person. But anyway that's the debate
you have by the חטאת. chatat. Okay. And now the גמרא Gemara
says, והדר ביה רבא. ve-hadar bei Rava. What?
Did I say I would say it doesn't?
Yeah, still it's your sin and if you don't want it to
work
there's some input into it to...
Yeah, if you don't want it to work why should it work
if you don't want it to work?
Okay and the other says since there is a sin and you're
bringing it even if you don't want it to work for you
it's going to be for the sin.
It's sort of secondary. Exactly. Okay so but anyway although that's a
nice conceptual מהלך, mahalach, the גמרא Gemara says רבא Rava reversed himself.
והדר ביה רבא. Ve-hadar bei Rava. רבא Rava reversed himself. כדתניא, Ki
tanya, like it was in a ברייתא. braita יכול יהא יום הכיפורים
מכפר על שבים ועל שאינם שבים? Yakhol yehei Yom HaKippurim mechaper al
shavim ve-al she-einam shavim? Maybe יום כיפור Yom Kippur will work even
for people that don't do תשובה. teshuvah. ודינו, Ve-dino, that actually makes
sense to say not that way. Why? ומה חטאת ואשם מכפרים ויום
הכיפורים מכפר. U-mah chatat ve-asham mechaperin ve-Yom HaKippurim mechaper. Because make it
comparable to חטאת chatat and אשם asham which atone and יום כיפור
Yom Kippur atones. So let's see how they work. מה חטאת ואשם
אין מכפרים אלא על שבים, Mah chatat ve-asham ein mechaperin ela al
shavim,
the same way חטאת chatat and an אשם asham only work for
people who do תשובה, teshuvah, אף יום הכיפורים אין מכפר אלא על
שבים. af Yom HaKippurim ein mechaper ela al shavim. Even יום כיפור
Yom Kippur
only atones for people who do תשובה. teshuvah. So maybe I should
say that? לא, מנל, Lo, minal, maybe not necessarily. אם אמרת בחטאת
ואשם שאין מכפרים על מזיד כשוגג. Im amarta be-chatat ve-asham she-ein mechaperin
al mazin ke-shogeg.
חטאת chatat and אשם asham don't work for intentional sins, only for
unintentional. So their atonement power is more limited. תאמר ביום הכיפורים שמכפר
על מזיד Tomar be-Yom HaKippurim she-mechaper al mazin שוגג shogeg יום כיפור's
Yom Kippur more powerful, it atones for intentional sins. והואיל ומכפר על
המזיד כשוגג מכפר על השבים ועל שאינם שבים. veho'il umechaper al hamazid
keshogeg mechaper al hashavim ve'al she'einam shavim. If it's that powerful that
it works on intentional sins, maybe it should work even if you
haven't done תשובה. teshuvah. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar אך. ach. אך בעשור
לחדש השביעי. ach be'asor lachodesh hashvi'i. Right, פסוק. אך בעשור לחדש השביעי.
ach be'asor lachodesh hashvi'i. No, that's יום
הכפורים הוא לה'. Yom hakippurim hu l'Hashem. Right. Okay, I guess that's
פסוק. Right. Okay, so anyway, אך חלק. ach chalak. So it's limited.
It's not by all of them, it's only by some things it
does not work for those who do not do תשובה. teshuvah. Okay,
so that's יום כיפור Yom Kippur doesn't work for those who do
not do תשובה. teshuvah. Now in the context of that, we've also
said that a חטאת chatat and אשם asham don't work for those
who don't do תשובה. teshuvah. Let's understand what we mean by that.
מאי שבים ושאינם שבים? mai shavim veshe'einam shavim? What do they mean
whether you have or have not done תשובה? teshuvah? אילימא שבים שוגג
לא שבים מזיד. ileima shavim shogeg lo shavim mazid. If it doesn't
really mean what you've done after the sin, but it means how,
you know, what your mindset was at the time of the sin.
שבים shavim means somebody that's an unintentional, לא שבים lo shavim means
an intentional sinner. And that's what the question was about יום כיפור
Yom Kippur and that's what we said certainly is not true by
a חטאת. chatat. אלא מאי דהא קתני לא אם אמרת בחטאת ואשם
וכו'. ela mai deha katani lo im amarta bechatat ve'asham vechu'. The
Gemara says you can't say that because when we're trying to figure
out שבים shavim and אינו שבים, eino shavim, we bring in the
parallel of does it work for שוגג shogeg and מזיד. mazid. So
שוגג shogeg and מזיד mazid is obviously not the same as the
תשובה teshuvah question. שוגג shogeg and מזיד mazid is a different issue.
That works for חטאת chatat and אשם. asham. חטאת chatat only שוגג,
shogeg, יום כיפור Yom Kippur even מזיד. mazid. אלא, so what's the
difference, what's the question of whether it works for those who haven't
done תשובה? teshuvah? כי הא דעולא אמר רבי יוחנן. ki ha de'Ulla
amar Rabbi Yochanan. Like Ulla said in the name of Rabbi Yochanan.
אכל חלב והפריש קרבן. achal chelev vehefrish korban.
Somebody ate חלב chelev and they set aside a קרבן korban to
atone בשוגג. beshogeg. והמיר דעתו. vehemir da'ato. And the person, you know,
basically rebelled, he rebelled against God, he gave up Judaism, he became
an אפיקורוס. apikoros. Okay, and then וחזר בו. vechazar bo. And now
he's done תשובה teshuvah and he wants to go back and bring
his קרבן. korban. הואיל ונדחה ידחה. ho'il venidcha yidcha.
Since at the time that he was a מומר, mumar, a מומר
mumar cannot bring a קרבן korban for any sin, even past or
whatever, he's excluded as a person from being a קרבן korban if
you're a rebel, a מומר, mumar, somebody who has rejected Judaism. So
therefore once the קרבן korban has been pushed away, it remains pushed
away. So maybe that's what we mean, that a קרבן korban does
not work for those that have not done תשובה, teshuvah, really means
somebody that has completely rebelled after the קרבן. korban. So the Gemara
says if that's true, no, נהי דאידחי קרבן גברא בר כפרה הוא.
nehi de'idchi korban gavra bar kaparah hu.
That type of a person is not completely excluded. He's excluded in
the moment of his rebellion, but when he does תשובה, teshuvah, he
will be able to bring the קרבן. korban. Maybe the קרבן korban
he set aside, not that one, but he'll be able to bring
a קרבן. korban. Can't he resanctify it? Right. No, that's a, that's
a, yeah, right, exactly. Anyway,
so the Gemara says we're not talking about somebody that's rebelled or
not because then we would not have said that a קרבן korban
doesn't work for that person, because it will work once he's done
תשובה. teshuvah. אלא, so what does it mean a קרבן korban doesn't
work for somebody who does not do תשובה? teshuvah? שבים דאמר יכפר
עלי חטאתי. shavim de'amar yechaper alai chatati.
שבים shavim is somebody that says let it work for me, my
חטאת. chatat. שאינם שבים דאמר לא תכפר עלי חטאתי. she'einam shavim de'amar
lo techaper alai chatati.
Let it not work for me. So therefore that's the only way
the Gemara could understand the difference by a חטאת chatat whether you've
done תשובה teshuvah or not, meaning are you at the time that
you bring it prepared to have it work for you. And since
it says that that's what a חטאת chatat only, חטאת chatat only
works for them, then it compares it to יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So presumably by יום כיפור Yom Kippur also it'll only work if
you say let יום כיפור Yom Kippur atone for me. שמע מינה,
shema mina, that's a good proof. So now based on the distinction
between שבים shavim and אינו שבים, eino shavim, the Gemara says that
a חטאת chatat only works if you want it to work for
you, not if you reject it working for you, as Rava basically
steps back from his earlier position that it works regardless. And similarly,
although there was a debate of Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish, does
יום כיפור Yom Kippur work if you don't want it to, we're
also saying now based on this ברייתא braisa that also יום כיפור
Yom Kippur like חטאת chatat only works if you want it to
work for you. Now the point though is, the question is, is
that there's an obvious much huger category that the Gemara's forgetting about
or it seems to be ignoring and I don't know the answer
to this. If I asked you does יום כיפור Yom Kippur work
for people who haven't done תשובה, teshuvah, right, would you say oh
what do you mean haven't done תשובה, teshuvah, do you mean like
you said oh I don't want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to work
for me? No, of course not, of course you want יום כיפור
Yom Kippur to work for you, you just haven't gone through a
process of תשובה, teshuvah, right? That's what you would have said if
you haven't done תשובה. teshuvah. Same thing by a חטאת. chatat. I
bring a חטאת, chatat, I'm happy to bring it, I want it
to work for me, I just haven't gone through a process of
תשובה, teshuvah, an inner process of תשובה. teshuvah. Why isn't the Gemara
talking about that? Does my חטאת chatat work if I haven't gone
through an inner process of תשובה? teshuvah? Does יום כיפור Yom Kippur
work if I haven't gone through an inner process of תשובה? teshuvah?
So it's a little bit unclear why the Gemara's completely ignoring that
and saying oh the only case we can figure out is if
you don't want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to work. It sounds like
from the Gemara that if you were שוגג shogeg to begin with,
remember you're not a מזיד mazid in these cases, right? You're a
שוגג, shogeg, although it's not true, יום כיפור Yom Kippur works even
for מזיד. mazid. But anyway, at least in the case of a
שוגג, shogeg, maybe if you're a שוגג shogeg combined with the fact
that you want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to work or you want
your קרבן korban to work, you're bringing your קרבן, korban, you're fasting
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and so on, maybe that's sufficient תשובה,
teshuvah, you know? But but again, it's funny that the Gemara is
ignoring that, especially also because on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you have
the whole case of מזיד. mazid. מזיד mazid it's obvious to discuss
the difference between having and not having
done תשובה. teshuva? I know, we're going to actually get into a
case of whether you fast. I threw that in to try exactly,
because it's so hard to say, well, you know, how can you
say you've done תשובה? teshuva, So I tried to say, well, maybe
the fasting qualifies as that for a שוגג. shogeg. But the גמרא's
Gemara actually going to get to that question in a minute. Do
is it also entail that you know required that you fast and
observe יום כיפור Yom Kippur as part of the process? But anyway,
it's quite fascinating and strange that the גמרא Gemara in searching for
an example of does חטאת chatas work haven't done תשובה, teshuva יום
כיפור Yom Kippur work, doesn't discuss the basic question of the inner
process of תשובה teshuva and only focuses on the question of whether
you want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to work or not. Yes.
So he basically רמי rami versus the... he has this ברייתא braisa
because it's right the...
this ברייתא braisa seems to say, at least the way he's reading
it, although it's not clear why he's reading it, but this ברייתא
braisa, says you need תשובה teshuva, for יום כיפור Yom Kippur and
חטאת. chatas. The גמרא Gemara is now saying what that means is
that not only you need תשובה, teshuva you need to say I
want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to work, I want the חטאת chatas
to work, but also seems to bracket the question of whether you've
done תשובה teshuva or not. Anyway, let's keep on going. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, where are we? So the
גמרא Gemara says like
this: שמע מינה. shma mina. ורמינהי, u'reminhi, I'll ask you on this
that it works regardless. We have another ברייתא, braisa. ספרא. Sifra. יכול
לא יהא יום הכפורים מכפר אלא על שנתענה בו ולא עשה בו
מלאכה וקראו מקרא
קודש. Yachol lo yehei Yom HaKippurim mechaper ela al shenitana bo velo
asa bo melacha vekara'o mikra kodesh. Maybe יום כיפור Yom Kippur only
works on somebody who fasts and doesn't do מלאכה melacha and declares
it a holy day. Let's say, you know, רש"י Rashi says here
it means that you davened or you dressed appropriately, whatever, you distinguished
it, you made it into a special day. לא נתענה בו ועשה
בו מלאכה ולא קראו מקרא קודש, Lo nitana bo ve'asa bo melacha
velo kara'o mikra kodesh, you didn't fast on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you did מלאכה, melacha, you didn't recognize, you know, the significance of
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you went to the beach instead. יכול לא
יהא יום הכפורים מכפר? Yachol lo yehei Yom HaKippurim mechaper? Maybe it
wouldn't atone? Yeah, I would think that that would stand to reason.
תלמוד לומר יום הכפורים הוא מכל מקום, Talmud lomar Yom HaKippurim hu
mikol makom, regardless. So this is pretty amazing. We have one set
of opinions that we've been hearing voiced that יום כיפור Yom Kippur
works even if you don't want it to work, even if you
say you don't want it to work. Not only that, it works
even on מזיד. meizid. We haven't said it works even if you
haven't done תשובה teshuva, yet, but it works even if you're violating
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it works. So anyway, וצריכא דתרוייהו סתם ספרא
הוא. u'tzricha detarvaihu stam Sifra hu. קשיא אהדדי. Kashya ahadadi. They're both
from the ספרא, Sifra, anonymous, so you can't say they're different תנא.
tanna. So they're contradicting, because one seems to be that you need
to want it to work, whereas the other says even if you
violate. Now of course you could imagine distinguishing those cases. Maybe I
need to want it to work. Yeah, I want יום כיפור Yom
Kippur to be מכפר mechaper for me as I am going ahead
and, you know, driving and eating and doing all these things on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. I still would like it to work for
me. Okay, so the גמרא, Gemara however, thinks that those are all
part of the same פרשה. parsha. If you need to be sort
of doing the right things on יום כיפור Yom Kippur for it
to work, then, you know, then you would need to want it
to work for you, you need to keep יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
and if you don't, then it would... and it works regardless, it
should work even regardless of not wanting it to work for you.
What about ישעיה Yeshaya says, you know, is this the kind of
fast that I, you know, you go and do these things and
you do יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
Right, right, and that's... but that's even not talking about violating יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, that's talking about not doing תשובה, teshuva. real... right.
So it's a good point. And the... and the גמרא Gemara did
say, you know, even... it doesn't work על שאינם שבים. al she'einam
shavim. But here it is making... I mean, it's pretty amazing, and
this is more explicit in יומא, Yoma, how radical some of the
opinions of some תנאים tannaim is, you know, that יום כיפור Yom
Kippur works... works regardless, which I mean, really speaks to the need
for atonement and being able to start fresh and, you know, an
appreciation of human frailty and so on. So obviously nobody's saying any
of this is ideal, but it's, you know, but there are some
radical opinions here about this.
And then somebody would say that I'll depend on that and then
I'll never do תשובה. teshuva.
Well, that's the question of אחטא ואשוב אחטא ואשוב ויום הכפורים מכפר.
Echeta ve'ashuv echeta ve'ashuv veYom HaKippurim mechaper. So that might... that might
remain excluded if at the moment of the sin you are doing
it with that in mind. Okay, so let's take a look at
how the גמרא Gemara answers. אמר אביי לא קשיא הא רבי אליבא
דרבי יהודה הא רבי אליבא דנפשיה. Amar Abaye lo kashya ha Rabbi
aliba deRabbi Yehuda ha Rabbi aliba denafshei. It's a רבי Rabbi according
to his own opinion, רבי Rabbi, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
because סתם ספרא stam Sifra is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, we
taught in the ברייתא. רבי אומר כל עבירות שבתורה בין עשה תשובה
בין לא עשה תשובה יום הכפורים מכפר. Rabbi omer kol aveiros shebaTorah
bein asa teshuva bein lo asa teshuva Yom HaKippurim mechaper. So there
you go. Before we said it only works if you have done...
if you have done תשובה. teshuva. Here רבי Rabbi himself says it
works even if you haven't done תשובה. teshuva. חוץ, Chutz, with the
one exception of, מפורק עול, miforek ol, if somebody completely rejects the
yoke of תורה ומצוות, Torah u'mitzvos, ומגלה פנים בתורה, umegaleh panim baTorah,
reveals faces in the תורה, Torah let's go back to that in
a second, ומיפר ברית בשר, umeifer bris basar, or... and... and has
gone and has basically, you know, annulled, you know, the
circumcision, the... the covenant of the flesh, because at what times in
the time of the תנאים tannaim and so on, especially, you know,
under the Greeks where or whatever, Hellenism, where there were Jews that
actually tried to reverse, do an operation to reverse circumcision. So those
type of people that are basically completely rejecting, that doesn't work if
you haven't done תשובה.
teshuva, Physical reversal.
Physical reversal. Oh yeah, physical reversal. שאם עשה תשובה יום הכפורים מכפר,
She'im asa teshuva Yom HaKippurim mechaper, but it doesn't mean you're completely
excluded. Even those that have completely rejected, if you do תשובה, teshuvah,
יום כיפור Yom Kippur will atone. ואם לאו אין יום הכפורים מכפר,
Ve'im lav ein Yom HaKippurim mechaper, if not it won't atone. Now
what is מגלה פנים? megaleh panim? Normally you would hear the phrase
מגלה פנים בתורה שלא כהלכה megaleh panim baTorah shelo kehalacha and we
think that it means like to reveal, to some... explicate or... רש"י
Rashi here says it means you make stupid דרשות, drashot, you interpret
the Torah, you present the Torah in false ways and so on.
But the original texts do not have שלא כהלכה. shelo k'halacha. The
original texts here and in the משניות Mishnayot in פרקי אבות Pirkei
Avot and other places just have מגלה פנים בתורה. megaleh panim b'Torah.
So the רמב"ם Rambam in his פירוש המשניות Perush Hamishnayot on פרקי
אבות Pirkei Avot in the second פרק perek where this appears says
that it quotes the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that interprets מגלה פנים megaleh panim
as like עזות פנים, azut panim, brazen, and quotes the פסוק דבר
ה' בזה, idvar Hashem bazah, which basically just means that you like
act brazenly towards the Torah, you know, you denigrate the Torah, you
completely, you know, not just sin, but you basically, you know, attack
it. And say things about it? Yeah, basically, you brazenly say this
is nonsense, this is garbage, and you presumably you act on the
basis of that, עושה ביד רמה. oseh b'yad ramah. That's the way
the רמב"ם Rambam understands it, which fits much better with the, you
know, with the cell, but then you wonder how is it exactly
different than פורק עול? porek ol? But okay. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says like this. So that's רבי. Rabbi So therefore what? So therefore
we're saying there are two opinions out there. One that יום כיפור
Yom Kippur works even without תשובה, teshuvah. and one that it needs
תשובה. teshuvah, Now what we're lining up, and again, you could have
distinguished all of these cases, but what we're lining up is the
question about תשובה, teshuvah, the question about if you don't observe יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, and the question about you say you don't want
יום כיפור Yom Kippur to work. So a position of רבי that
says you don't need to do תשובה, teshuvah, even that you don't
need to, whatever, it works without תשובה, teshuvah would also say, says
the גמרא, it works even if you violated it, and would work
even if you said you didn't want יום כיפור Yom Kippur to
work. And the position that says you need תשובה teshuvah says it
only works if you keep יום כיפור Yom Kippur and only works
if you did not violate, if you did not say you did
not want it to work. And again, you could have distinguished any
of those and said one yes to one, no to the other,
but the גמרא is lining them all up in the same category.
You get rid of any middle position.
You get rid of any middle position, right. The גמרא is consistently
saying it's all or nothing. Okay, that's one answer.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, הא והא רבי. ha v'ha Rabbi. It's אליבא
דנפשיה. aliba d'nafshei. It's really רבי. Now here the גמרא is finally
distinguishing some of the categories. It's both
רבי. ומודה רבי בעבירות דיום הכיפורים גופיה דלא מכפר. U'modeh Rabbi b'aveirot
d'Yom HaKippurim gufei d'lo mechaper. When רבי said that יום כיפור Yom
Kippur is not מכפר, mechaper, when he says earlier back, what was
the statement back that it's לא עשה תשובה אינה מכפר? lo asah
teshuvah einah mechaper? What he means is that if you didn't do
תשובה teshuvah it doesn't atone, it means on the sins of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur itself. If you actually violated יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
then it will only atone if you've done תשובה teshuvah, on those
sins. ואי לא תימא הכי, V'ee lo teima hachi, if you don't
say that, I'm sorry, if you don't say that, that that's an
exclusion and that יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones even if you haven't
done
תשובה, teshuvah, כרת דיום הכיפורים לרבי, kares d'Yom HaKippurim l'Rabbi, how would
you ever get כרת kares for violating יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Right?
If יום כיפור Yom Kippur works even if you haven't kept it,
and if it works even if you haven't done תשובה, teshuvah. so
then you'll never get כרת kares for violating יום כיפור Yom Kippur
because it's going to work for you even if you haven't kept
יום כיפור Yom Kippur and it'll work even if you haven't done
תשובה. teshuvah, As soon as you do the sin, you're atoned for
it. So how are you ever going to get כרת kares, for
יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Well, okay, so let's see what the גמרא
says. Maybe. So כיון דבכל שעתא ושעתא מכפר, keivan d'bechol shaita v'shaita
mechaper, היכי משכחת לה? heichi mishkachat lah? How would you ever get
it? So it must be even according to רבי, it doesn't work
for the sins of יום כיפור Yom Kippur at the
end of the day and you die.
All right, so the גמרא says, ומאי קושיא? u'mai kushi? Why is
that difficult? דילמא דעבד עבידתא כולי ליליא, Dilma d'avid avidta kulei leilya,
you did a מלאכה melachah the whole night of יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, every during כל נדרי Kol Nidrei you were doing מלאכה, melachah,
ובדיממא דשחמי ומת, u'badiyomah d'shachamei u'meit, and you died before daybreak, דלא
הוי יממא דלכפר ליה, d'lo havi yimama d'lechaper lei, that the day
isn't atoning because כי ביום הזה יכפר עליכם, ki bayom hazeh yechaper
aleichem, עיצומו של יום מכפר, itzumo shel yom mechaper, the day atones,
not the night. So the atonement covers the day. So maybe that's
one way. In the day. So the גמרא says, תינח, tenach, yeah,
presumably at
the end of the day, at the end of the day.
All right, תינח כרת דליליא. tenach kares d'leilya. That's good for getting
כרת kares, at night. כרת דיממא היכי משכחת לה? Kares d'yimama heichi
mishkachat lah? How could you ever get כרת kares. for violating it
in the day? So the גמרא says, right, because it says anybody
who eats, you know, מתשעה לחודש לחבר, mitishah lachodesh lachaver, whatever, anyway,
so clearly you can get כרת kares even in the day. גמרא
says, ומאי קושיא? u'mai kushi? Why is that difficult? דילמא בהדי דקא
אכיל נמה חנקדיה ומת, Dilma bahadi d'ka achol namah chankadei u'meit, maybe
as you were eating bread you choked on, you know, on some
piece of meat or whatever, you were eating, you choked, and therefore
you died. You died in the middle of the מלאכה, melachah, so
you were not atoned for. Presumably what the גמרא is assuming is
that it doesn't atone as you're doing the איסור, issur, maybe a
second after, but not as. Okay, anyway, ומת, u'meit, and you died,
דלא הוי ליה שעות דיממא דלכפר ליה, d'lo havi lei sha'os d'yimama
d'lechaper lei, you didn't have a moment afterwards to atone. אי נמי
דעבד עבידתא סמוך לשקיעת החמה, Ee nami d'avid avidta samuch l'shkias chamah,
you did it right before sunset and the day right into צאת,
tzeit, so you were doing מלאכה melachah constantly until it became night,
until it became מוצאי יום כיפור. motzei Yom Kippur. אי נמי, Ee
nami, or, בהדי דעבד עבידתא, bahadi d'avid avidta, as you're doing a
מלאכה, melachah, פסיק מרא לשקיה, pasik mara l'shakei, you were maybe chopping
wood on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the axe cut off your
thigh and you died there in the moment of doing מלאכה. melachah.
Another example of dying at the moment of doing מלאכה. melachah. ומת,
u'meit, דלא הוי ליה שעות דיממא דלכפר ליה, d'lo havi lei sha'os
d'yimama d'lechaper lei, you didn't have a moment for the day to
atone. So it's assuming that it won't atone at the exact moment.
It will then. Okay, so it's not a proof that רבי would
exclude that, but saying maybe at least רבי would exclude that case.
But again, what's pretty amazing is that the גמרא is... basically puts
all these things together. If יום כפור Yom Kippur works even if
you don't want it to work, then with that comes the idea
that it works even without תשובה, teshuvah, even if you say that
you don't want יום כפור Yom Kippur to atone, even if you
violate יום כפור, Yom Kippur, all of those things, like you could
distinguish any one, but גמרא says no, it works regardless, as opposed
to position you need to do תשובה, teshuvah you need to want
it to atone, you need to not violate יום כפור, Yom Kippur,
and so on. And the one thing גמרא excluded from that huge
list of it works regardless is maybe it doesn't work for sin
of יום כפור Yom Kippur itself as you're not doing תשובה and
violating יום כפור. Yom Kippur. That maybe is the one thing in
that huge list that it doesn't work for. Okay, anyway, that was
a fascinating discussion, a digression about the issue about why it mentioned
אשם תלוי, asham talui, why did it exclude the case of יום
כפור?
Yom Kippur? Why wouldn't it work if
we don't want it to? But yeah, the גמרא never, well, it
did seem to have a debate about whether, right, the גמרא never
actually, no, the גמרא starts with a מחלוקת אביי ורבא machloket Abaye
ve-Rava but whether your חטאת chatas works, says רבא Rava reversed himself,
but that's based on the discussion of יום כפור Yom Kippur which
in the end is debated, so it's not so clear if in
the end we would say that רבא Rava completely reversed himself about
the חטאת. chatas. Okay now, now back to the case of מגדף.
megadef. הא מי מאימא אף מגדף? Ha mi mai-ima af megadef? Once
we're excluding things from an אשם, asham, the חכמים Chachamim said, oh,
what we also need to exclude from the חטאת chatas is a
מגדף megadef because it doesn't have an action, and we discussed this
before. מאי אף מגדף? Mai af megadef? What does it mean even
מגדף? megadef? We didn't list anything else that was excluded from a
חטאת, chatas, we list excluded from an אשם תלוי, asham talui, not
from a חטאת. chatas. רבנן שמעו ליה לרבי עקיבא דתני בעל אוב.
Rabbanan shamlei le-Rabbi Akiva de-tani ba'al ov. No, because the Rabbis heard
that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, only put in his list בעל אוב.
ba'al ov. ולא תני ידעוני. Ve-lo tani yidoni. He didn't mention ידעוני,
yidoni, right, which is you put the bone in the mouth but
you don't do any action. אמרו ליה מאי שנא דלא מייתי קרבן?
Amru lei mai shna de-lo maisi korban? Why do you רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva who is the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, why are you
not assuming you don't bring a קרבן korban for ידעוני? yidoni? משום
דלית ביה מעשה. Mishum de-leis bei ma'aseh. Because there's no action. מגדף
נמי לית ביה מעשה. Megadef nami leis bei ma'aseh. Also מגדף. megadef.
That's the אף. Even a מגדף. megadef. You are implicitly excluding a
ידעוני, yidoni, even a מגדף megadef should be excluded, also no action.
And if you remember before, the גמרא said two explanations about רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva why he distinguishes between ידעוני yidoni and מגדף. megadef.
Either he requires an action but it's a very minimal standard, and
מגדף megadef he has the verbal action, or he doesn't require an
action and the only reason he excluded ידעוני yidoni was because it
was only one לאו. And since it was only one לאו, therefore
you are not going to bring two different קרבנות korbanos for אוב
וידעוני, ov ve-yidoni, but you would really bring for either of them.
Okay. Now the גמרא says like this. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan, מגדף
מייתי קרבן הואיל ובא בו כרת דברי רבי עקיבא. megadef meivi korban
ho'il u-ba bo kares divrei Rabbi Akiva. Brings a קרבן korban because
it says כרת, kares presumably regardless even though it doesn't have an
action. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, says. So that sounds like
you don't need an action, it says כרת, kares, end of story.
You bring the חטאת. chatas. ונשא חטאו. Ve-nasah chet'o. And it says
that he will carry his sin. That
and that means כרת. kares So the גמרא says: וכלל הוא? u-khlal
hu? Is that really a general principle? כל היכא דכתיב ביה כרת
מייתי קרבן? Kol heicha de-ksiv bei kares maisi korban? Are you really
saying every time it says כרת kares. you bring a קרבן? korban?
בפסח ומילה דכתיב ביה כרת ולא מייתי קרבן. Ba-pesach u-milah de-ksiv bei
kares ve-lo maisi korban. How about פסח ומילה? pesach u-milah? It says
כרת kares, and there's no קרבן. korban. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, right,
because it's a מצות עשה, mitzvas asei, it's not a לא תעשה.
lo sa'aseh. So this is what he means. מגדף מייתי קרבן הואיל
ובא בו הכרת במקום קרבן דברי רבי עקיבא. Megadef meivi korban ho'il
u-ba bo hakares bi-mkom korban divrei Rabbi Akiva. Because
in where the תורה Torah mentions מגדף, megadef, it actually juxtaposes it
to a קרבן. korban. And therefore specifically by כרת, kares, by מגדף,
megadef, does the mention of not every כרת kares, brings a קרבן,
korban, it's true, there is פסח ומילה, pesach u-milah, but specifically by
מגדף megadef there is. Why? What does the תורה say? So here
in במדבר Bamidbar 15, the end of שלח, Shelach, it says the
following: ונפש אחת תחטא בשגגה והקריבה עז בת שנתה לחטאת. ve-nefesh achas
techeta bi-shgagah ve-hikrivah ez bas shnasah le-chatas. So
that's if you do a sin by, you know, unintentionally you bring
a חטאת. chatas. And then it says that where is it? והנפש
אשר תעשה ביד רמה מן האזרח ומן הגר, ve-hanefesh asher ta'aseh be-yad
ramah min ha-ezrach u-min ha-ger,
but if you did with an outstretched arm, which means you did
it willfully, then you don't get a חטאת. chatas. את ה' הוא
מגדף. Es Hashem hu megadef. Then you are blaspheming God. ונכרתה הנפש
ההיא מקרב עמה. ve-nikhresah hanefesh ha-hi mi-kerev ammah. You get כרת. kares
So he says there, not everybody gets כרת, kares but there it
says the way it frames, you know, in the idea of getting
כרת, kares speaks about מגדף, megadef, blaspheming God, 15:30,
and it's juxtaposed to if it was בשגגה bi-shgogah you bring a
חטאת. chatas. So right there where it talks about מגדף megadef and
getting כרת, kares it talks about בשגגה bi-shgogah bringing a חטאת. chatas.
So that's how I know that a כרת kares brings, that a
מגדף megadef brings a חטאת. chatas. Of course פשט הפסוקים pshat ha-psukim
you would say it means through your actions you're blaspheming God, it's
not the sin of blaspheming, but he says nevertheless it talks about
blaspheming getting כרת kares? juxtaposed to bringing a קרבן, korban, so מגדף
megadef brings a קרבן. korban. דברי רבי עקיבא. Divrei Rabbi Akiva. Right,
we can't take any, right, no commentary. קסבר מידי דבעי מכתב כרת
בעלמא, Kasavar migu de-ba'i mikhtav kares be-alma,
could have mentioned כרת kares. in general, וכתיב כרת במקום קרבן, u-khsiv
kares bi-mkom korban, and it says it here by a קרבן korban
and not just any קרבן, korban, but a כרת kares, about מגדף,
megadef, it says right next to a קרבן, korban, שמע מינה מייתי
קרבן. shma minah maisi korban. You see that a מגדף megadef brings
a קרבן. korban. Okay, now. וחטאו ישא. Ve-chet'o yisa.
And it says he shall carry the sin. That's not from that
same
אמריתו, Amrisu, your problem was מגדף חוץ מן המעשה. Megadef chutz min
hama'aseh. So you
say it has no action. מה הוא מגדף מברך את השם? Mah
hu Megadef mevarech es Hashem? Because that's cursing God. אלא
כרת דכתיב למה אתא? Ela kares d'chsiv lama asa?
So I just quoted you a פסוק that says כרת kares. by
מגדף Megadef and it says juxtaposed to, you know, קרבן. korban. What
is the purpose of saying כרת? kares So אמר ליה, ליתן כרת
למקלל. liten kares l'mekalel.
No, to tell you, not to tell you that you bring a
קרבן, korban, but to tell you that you get כרת. kares? דכתיב
במקלל, D'chsiv b'mekalel, it says by the case of the מקלל, mekalel,
this is at the, you know, at the ויקרא כ"ד, Vayikra chaf-daled,
right, by the בני ישראלית, Bnei Yisraelis, right, the guy ויצא ויקלל,
vayeitzei vayekalel, right,
the actual event of the person cursing God. And it says there,
the פסוק is on the side, ונשא חטאו. v'nasa chet'o. וכתיב פסח
שני חטאו ישא. U'chsiv Pesach Sheni chet'o yisa. It says by פסח
שני Pesach Sheni carry the sin and there it says carry the
sin. מה להלן כרת אף כאן כרת. Mah lehalan kares af kan
kares. The same way there you get כרת, kares here you get
כרת. kares, Because there's a whole question if somebody doesn't bring a
פסח שני Pesach Sheni do they get כרת kares, or not? They
were exempt of פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, they were טמא, tamei, בדרך
רחוקה, b'derech rechoka, they didn't bring a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, did
they get כרת? kares. The פסוק says ונשא חטאו. v'nasa chet'o. Does
ונשא חטאו v'nasa chet'o mean כרת kares or not? So what he
is, the חכמים Chachamim here are saying is, is that we hold
that a person who brings, that that type of a person, yes,
does get כרת, kares, doesn't bring פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. It's linked
to the מקלל mekalel to tell you the מקלל mekalel gets כרת,
kares, or the מקלל mekalel is linked to it, or whatever, either
way. And therefore you get כרת. kares And that's why it says
כרת kares? by the מקלל, mekalel, to tell you the מקלל mekalel
gets כרת, kares. קרבן פסח korban Pesach gets כרת, kares but not
to tell you there's a חטאת. chatas. Okay, fine. I mean that
wasn't so interesting, that גרסא, girsa, but that's the way we have
it. רש"י Rashi has a different גרסא, girsa, which actually says that
no, the חכמים Chachamim are saying back
to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva hold on let me just check רש"י
Rashi again.
Right. So they're saying back to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva the following
way. They're saying first of all we don't agree with you. We
think the מגדף Megadef mentioned there where it says את השם הוא
מגדף es Hashem hu Megadef and the juxtaposition is that you bring
a חטאת, chatas, that's not talking about cursing God. That's talking about
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. A certain form of עבודה זרה.
avoda zara.
Not the פסוק at the end of ויקרא, Vayikra, which is clearly
about cursing God, but the פסוק about את השם הוא מגדף, es
Hashem hu Megadef, which it says here in במדבר ט"ו, Bamidbar tes-vav,
that he says is talking about, that he says is talking about
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Now not classic עבודה זרה, avoda zara, because
then you wouldn't need a special פסוק for the whole thing, but
a type of the way like, you know, רש"י Rashi says or
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, like singing or dancing by עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, some type of a ritual act in front of an
idol that is not classic עבודה זרה. avoda zara. They say that's
the את השם הוא מגדף es Hashem hu Megadef that's mentioned over
there. And that you get כרת kares and that you bring a
חטאת chatas if you did it בשוגג. b'shogeg. So it says, alright,
you said you want to learn from over there that you get
חטאת chatas by שוגג shogeg by cursing God. We don't think that
מגדף Megadef refers to that. We think מגדף Megadef refers to a
form of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So if that's true, how do
they know that the general guy that curses and blasphemes God, how
do they know he gets כרת? So that is the גזירה שוה
gezeira shava to פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. By פסח שני Pesach Sheni
it says ונשא חטאו. v'nasa chet'o. By the guy who's מקלל אלוהיו,
mekalel Elokav, איש איש כי יקלל אלוהיו ונשא חטאו. ish ish ki
yekalel Elokav v'nasa chet'o. So from there we learn that the guy
who curses God gets כרת. But your פסוק that you said, it
said מגדף Megadef next to a קרבן korban and he brings a
קרבן, korban, we don't think that מגדף Megadef is a person who's
cursing God. We think that's a form of עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
Yeah, so that's why it's not חייב מיתה. chayav misa. That's why
it's only כרת and a קרבן, korban, because it's not one of
the four classic עבודות. avodos. Okay, let's just finish to the משנה.
תנו רבנן, את השם הוא
מגדף. es Hashem hu Megadef. איסי בן יהודה אומר, Issi ben Yehuda
omer, כאדם האומר לחבירו גירסת הקערה וחיסרת. k'adam ha'omer l'chaveiro geirasta hake'ara
v'chisarta. Like somebody who said to a friend, you know, you cleaned
out the bowl, like a bowl of porridge or soup, let's imagine
it was a wood bowl, and you actually took away from it,
you scraped it so much to the bottom of the bowl that
you scraped away from the bowl itself. That cursing God is like
actually attacking God Godself. So that's what את השם הוא מגדף. es
Hashem hu Megadef. מכסבר
מגדף מברך את השם. Mikasvar Megadef mevarech es Hashem. So that's cursing
God. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer, כאדם
האומר לחבירו גירסת הקערה, k'adam ha'omer l'chaveiro geirasta hake'ara, like מגדף, Megadef,
מגרף, megaref, you cleaned out the bowl, ולא חיסרת, v'lo chisarta,
but you did not actually scrape anything away from the bottom. You
just cleaned it out, but you didn't actually get to the bowl
itself. כסבר מגדף היינו עובד עבודה זרה. Kasvar Megadef hainu oved avoda
zara. That's עבודה זרה, avoda zara, which is wild, but רש"י Rashi
and רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom both say that what it's saying is
עובד עבודה זרה oved avoda zara is not actually attacking God. It's
only עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Now what does that mean? Because we
think, right, עבודה זרה avoda zara is the worst, you're completely rejecting
God, you're worshipping other things. But, you know, the רמב"ם Rambam actually
says something almost very parallel to this. The רמב"ם Rambam in מורה
נבוכים, Moreh Nevuchim, the רמב"ם Rambam who said that if somebody is
not מודה, modeh, he doesn't have חלק לעולם הבא, chelek l'olam haba,
who believes that God has a body and so on, and the
ראב"ד Ra'avad classically responded to that and said, you know, there were
people that read the פסוקים, thought that God had a body. How
could you the innocent mistakes, how could you say that they don't
have עולם הבא? olam haba? So the רמב"ם Rambam says, "Well, let's
say somebody is עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah because he doesn't
know any better? I'll also say he doesn't have עולם הבא." olam
haba. And then he says, "And which is worse, to be עובד
עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah or to think something wrong about a
belief in God? Clearly, to think something wrong about a belief in
God is worse." This is what the רמב"ם Rambam says. Just you
know, it's sort of theological mindset because עבודה זרה avodah zarah doesn't
mean, first of all, his frame of עבודה זרה avodah zarah could
mean you believe in God, you're just worshipping God through an image.
Okay, or it means that you're worshipping other gods, but it doesn't
mean that you think something different about God. Your belief in God
is pure. You're just worshipping God the wrong way or you're worshipping
other gods. So that seems completely bizarre, but the רמב"ם Rambam in
מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevukhim says that, I mean to our intuition, and
that's what this גמרא seems to say. מגדף, Megadef, attacking God, cursing
God, somehow is worse than עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, which is funny
because עבודה זרה avodah zarah you get מיתה, misa, you don't get
מיתה misa from מגדף. megadef. And now we'll just end it up.
תניא אידך, Tanya idach, את ה', et Hashem, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah omer, בעובד עבודה זרה כתיב, be'oved avodah
zarah ketiv, הכתוב מדבר, hakasuv medaber, את ה' הוא מגדף זה עבודה
זרה. et Hashem hu megadef zeh avodah zarah. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim,
לא בא הכתוב אלא ליתן כרת למברך את ה'. lo ba hakasuv
ela litein kares l'mevarech et Hashem. No, it's not עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah,
it is cursing God, you get כרת whether you get a קרבן
korban or not is the debate of רבי עקיבא and the חכמים.
Chachamim.